Guide to the C.B. van Niel Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
C.B. van Niel papers
1923-1977
SC0325
Niel, Cornelis Bernardus van, 1897-1986
6.25 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of the estate of C.B. van Niel,1985
Information about Access
None.
Biography
In 1929, Dr. C. B. van Niel (1897-1985) started his career as an associate professor at the Jacques Loeb Laboratory, Hopkins Marine Station, Stanford University. He was appointed Herzstein Professor of Microbiology in 1946.
Dr. van Niel received his bachelor's degree in chemical engineering from Technical University, Delft, in 1923; in 1928 he was conferred a doctoral degree from the same University. His research, after coming to the Marine Station, was concerned mainly with photosynthesis, photosynthetic bacteria, and bacterial taxonomy. However, Dr. van Niel--Kees to his colleagues and students-- was interested in a much broader spectrum of questions and encouraged investigations on wider range of phenomena in his laboratory. His lectures attracted not only Stanford students, but students around the country. The numerous well-written lecture/seminar notes in this collection, mostly with diagrams and images that he planed to draw on blackboard, illuminate how well he prepared for these lectures. Although he enjoyed a friendly relationship with these students, the "gang", he was rigorous in their academic training. A long letter (hand-written first and then typed) to one of his doctoral students with detailed instruction on the student's dissertation shows van Niel as a serious and responsible professor.
By devoting an enormous amount of time translating articles published by Dr. Kluyver, van Niel's advisor at Technical University, and Dr. Pringsheim, van Niel showed his gratitude and respect to his senior microbiologists and their works. Same attitude can be seen from publications of the later part of his career. In these articles he analyzed old and current articles on the subject he was dealing with and provided well-woven stories on research history. Probably because of his appreciation of history, (among his papers is a bibliography on American history, possibly given to him by a history professor) he wrote an autobiography, "The Education of a Microbiologist: Some Reflections." (1967), which sums up his major scientific achievements and his teaching career.
Dr. van Niel also actively participated in academic/professional associations such as the Society of American Bacteriologists in the 1950s and the American Type Culture Collections in the 1960s. However, as he recalled in his autobiography, these and other activities were taking up too much of his time and gradually made direct participation in experimental study difficult. He finally decided to retire from the Marine Station in 1962. From 1964 to 1968 he taught at U.C. Santa Cruz as a visiting professor. After 1972, he threw out his collection of reprints and scientific books and totally gave up research and teaching. Death took him in 1985.
Scope and Content
The van Niel papers primarily document C. B. van Niel's career at the Hopkins Marine Station of Stanford University, his participation in preeminent scientific associations, and his role as a leader in the field of microbiology. The papers include ATCC documents, teaching materials, research notes, publications, correspondences, photographs, audiotapes, and medals.
The American Type Culture Collection (ATCC) papers delineate activities of the association when van Niel served as a board member in the early 1960s. Teaching Materials include course outlines, exam questions, lecture notes, and seminar notes, written between 1929 and 1968. Publications include his articles published from 1923 to 1972. Many of the hand-written drafts and galley proofs accompany these publications. The records of van Niel's research in the Yellowstone National Park, including admission letter, experimental summary, notes, and drafts, are grouped together under the article's title, Report on Preliminary Observations on the Microflora in and Near the Hot Spring in Yellowstone National Part and Their Importance for the Geological Formation, to preserve its entirety. Research Files mainly comprise his experimental summaries, experimental procedures, notes, charts, and bibliographies. Van Niel's correspondence (1924-1977) centers on themes of research, publication, and student's dissertations. One exception is a letter to his son on personal matters. Correspondents include C. E. Clifton (1904- ), Seymour S. Cohen (1919- ), Lois Epel, Helge Larsen, Jack London [a student from UCLA], Beryl V. Daniel, J. R. Porter, Hosmer W. Stone, and Charles H. Walkinshaw.
When compiling SELECTED PAPERS OF E.G. PRINGSHEIM, van Niel corresponded with Dr. Pringsheim, Mrs. Pringsheim, Selman A. Waksman (1888-1973), and Vernon Bryson (1913- ) between 1960 and 1964. These letters, together with the galley proofs for this book, are put under the series of SELECTED PAPERS OF E.G. PRINGSHEIM. Dr. Kluyver's Birthday Celebration and Obituary includes van Niel's writings about his teacher, Dr. Kluyver (1888-1956), the telegram to van Niel about Kluyver's death in 1956, and many obituaries written by other scholars.
The photographs files include images of microbiology, people (mostly scholars) and landscapes. Important medals van Niel won from 1939 to 1977 demonstrate him as a leading figure in science. Audiotapes recorded van Niel's 1962 lectures on experiments. Oversized Materials are certificates of honorary doctoral degree, honorary member, and award.
Access Terms
American Type Culture Collection..; Bryson, Vernon,, 1913-; Clifton, C. E.,, 1904-; Cohen, Seymour S., (Seymour Stanley), 1917-; Daniel, Beryl V.; Epel, Lois.; Hopkins Marine Station -- General subdivision--Faculty.;; Larsen, Helge.; London, Jack,, 1876-1916.; Porter, J. R.; Pringsheim, Ernst G., (Ernst Georg), 1881-; Stone, Hosmer W.; Waksman, Selman A., (Selman Abraham), 1888-1973.; Walkinshaw, Charles H.; Algae.; Bacteria--Classification.; Biochemistry.; Candida albicans.; Microbiology.; Photosynthesis.; Photosynthetic bacteria.
Collection Contents
- American Type Culture Collection (ATCC)
  - Budgets, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Budgets, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Budgets, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Budgets, 1964-1965 / Unknown Dates (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes / Agendas, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes / Agendas, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Personnel Records (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Policies / Constitution / Memo / Proposal, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Policies / Constitution / Memo / Proposal, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Reports (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Symposium Programs (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Teaching Materials
  - 1929-1931 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1932 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1935-1938 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1941 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1942-1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1954 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1955-1958 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1958 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1961 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1961 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1962 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1962 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1964 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1964 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1968 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1968 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Unknown Date (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Unknown Date (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Publications
  - Lists of Dr. Van Niel's Publications; and The Absence of Enhancement (Emerson Effect) in the Photosynthesis of Rhodospirillum Rubrum, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Bacterial Photosyntheses and Their Importance for the General Problem of Photosynthesis, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Biochemical Problems of the Chemo-Autotrophic Bacteria, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Biochemistry of Bacteria, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - The Biochemistry of Micro-Organisms: An Approach to General and Comparative Biochemistry, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Book Reviews, A Brief Survey of the Photosynthetic Bacteria, 1927,1928, 1952, 1963, 1965, Unknown Date; 1963 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Bacteria. Chapter 3 of Ward and Whipple's Freshwater Biology, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Bacteria. Chapter 3 of Ward and Whipple's Freshwater Biology, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - A Chemical Approach to the Problem of Biological Syntheses. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - The Concept of Bacterium, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - The Comparative Biochemistry of Photosynthesis, Delft School, The Education of a Microbiologist: Some Reflections, 1949 1949; 1967 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - The Education of a Microbiologist: Some Reflections, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - The Education of a Microbiologist: Some Reflections, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Experiments on Bacterial Denitrification, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Enzymatic Synthesis of Dextian. The Free Amino Groups of the Proteus Flagella Protein. Insect Microbiology. Introductory Remarks on the Comparative Biochemistry of Microorganism, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - John M. Prather Lectures, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The Chemistry and Physiology of Growth, Lipmann's Concepts of the Metabolic Generation and Utilization of Phosphate Bond Energy: A Historical Appreciation, Lipmann Dedicatory Volume: Notice to Contributors., 1949 1966 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Bacterial Metabolism. In McGraw-Hill Encyclopedia of Science and Technology, Bacteriology. In McGraw-Hill Encyclopedia of Science and Technology, and Microbiology. In McGraw-Hill Encyclopedia of Science and Technology, 1960; 1960; 1960 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - The Mechanism of Propionic Acid Formation and Succinate Decarboxylation. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - The Microbe as a Whole, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - A Note on Pseudomonas Stutzeri, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Microbiology and Molecular Biology, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Microbiology and Molecular Biology, A Note on the Apparent Absence of Azotobacter in Soils, 1966 1935 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - On the Mechanism of Ballistospore Discharge, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - On the Energetics of the Photosyntheses in Green Sulfur Bacteria, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - On the Energetics of the Photosyntheses in Green Sulfur Bacteria, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - On the Metabolism of Candida Albicans, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - On the Metabolism of Candida Albicans, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - On the Metabolism of the Thiorhodaceae, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - On the Morphology and Physiology of the Purple and Green Sulfur Bacteria, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - On the Morphology and Physiology of the Purple and Green Sulfur Bacteria, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - On the Morphology and Physiology of the Purple and Green Sulfur Bacteria, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - On the Morphology and Physiology of the Purple and Green Sulfur Bacteria, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - On the Photochemical Reduction of Nitrate by Algae, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - On Photosynthesis in the Presence of Hydroxylamine. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - On the Purple Bacteria and Their Significance for the Study of Photosynthesis, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - On the Purple Bacteria and Their Significance for the Study of Photosynthesis, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - On Radicalism and Conservatism in Science, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Photosynthetic Process of Purple Bacteria. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Photosynthesis of Bacteria, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Prospects for a Natural System of Classification of Bacteria, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Perspectives in Microbiology. (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Radioactive Carbon as an Indicator of Carbon Dioxide Utilization, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Reflection on Evaluation and Spontaneous Generation. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Report on Preliminary Observations on the Microflora in and Near the Hot Spring in Yellowstone National Park and Their Importance for the Geological Formation, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Report on Preliminary Observations on the Microflora in and Near the Hot Spring in Yellowstone National Park and Their Importance for the Geological Formation, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Report on Preliminary Observations on the Microflora in and Near the Hot Spring in Yellowstone National Park and Their Importance for the Geological Formation, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Techniques for the Enrichment, Isolation and Maintenance of the Photosynthetic Bacteria, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Ueber die Beweglichkeit und das Vorkommen von Geiszeln bei einigen Sarcina-Arten, De wijzen van voortbeweging van Mikroorganismen, Notiz uber die quantitative Bestimmung von Diacetyl Acetyl-Methylcarbinol, Les Photosyntheses Bacteriennes, 1923 1926 1927 1936 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Articles: Title Unknown. (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Research Files
  - Subject, A-E (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Subject, F-M (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Subject, M (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Subject, M (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Subject, N-Q (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Subject, R (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Subject, R (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Subject, R (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Subject, S (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Subject, S-V (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Subject, W-Z (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Notebook (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Notebooks (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Correspondence
  - Out-going Letters by Dr. Van Niel, 1924, 1942-1952 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Out-going Letters by Dr. Van Niel, 1955-1977 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - In-coming Letters, A-J (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - In-coming Letters, L (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - In-coming Letters, M-W (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - In-coming Letters, Sender Unknown (Box 10)
- Selected Papers of E.G. Pringsheim
  - Correspondence for Selected Papers of E.G. Pringsheim, Symposium Program, Symposium in Celebration of Dr. Pringsheim's 80th Birthday, 1960-1961; 1961 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence for Selected Papers of E.G. Pringsheim, 1962-1964 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence for Selected Papers of E.G. Pringsheim, date unknown (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Publications and Galley Proofs for Selected Papers of E.G. Pringsheim (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Publications and Galley Proofs for Selected Papers of E.G. Pringsheim (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Publications and Galley Proofs for Selected Papers of E.G. Pringsheim (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Publications and Galley Proofs for Selected Papers of E.G. Pringsheim (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Dr. Kluyver's Birthday Celebration and Obituary
  - "Professor A, J, Kluyver." By Dr. Van Niel, In celebration of Dr. Kluyver's Birthday (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Kluyver's Obituaries (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Other Scholar's Publications / Papers
  - Author, A-C (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Author, C (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Author, C (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Author, C (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Author, C (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Author, D-G (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Author, H-I (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Author, K-L (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Author, L (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Author, L (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Author, M-N (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Author, O-Q (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Author, R-S (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Author, S-W (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Author Unknown (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Student Paper, Author Unknown (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Photographs
  - Sporobolomyces Cultures (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Sporobolomyces Cultures (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Sporobolomyces Cultures (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Microbiology (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - People (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Landscape (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Medals (Box 15)
  - Third International Congress for Microbiology, 1939
  - Princeton University Bicentennial, 1946
  - George Westinghouse Centennial, 1946
  - L'Institut Pasteur, 1955-1956
  - Scientiae Medicinae Artiqve Salvtari, 1958
  - Koninklijke Nederlands Akademie van Wetenschappen, 1958
  - National Academy of Sciences Centennial, 1963
  - National Academy of Sciences Centennial, 1963
  - Rumford Medal for Discoveries in Light or Heat, 1967
  - Rumford Medal for Discoveries in Light or Heat, 1967
  - American Society for Microbiology, 1974
  - Deutsche Akademie der Naturforscher Leopoldina, 1977
  - Emil Chr. Hansen, Unknown Date
  - Institut Pasteur, Unknown Date
  - Toegewezen Door de Koninklijke Akademie van Wetenschappen te Amsterdam, Unknown date
  - National Medal of Science, Unknown Date
- Audiotapes
  - Yeast Cake c. viability of cells (Lab I), 6/25/-- (Box 16, Reel 6 (5 of 8))
  - Wild Yeast A. Fruit and Flower Yeasts 13 Ham Yeasts (Lab II) (Box 16, Reel 9)
  - General Yeast Experiments C. Fermentation (Lab III) (Box 16, Reel 12 (3 of 4))
  - General Yeast Experiments. C. Fermentation D. Dalmau E. Trigonopsis Variabilis F. Nuclear Stains G. Sporobolomyces H. Mucor Racemosus (Lab III) (Box 16, Reel 13)
  - Lactic Acid Bacteria A-B (Lab IV) (Box 16, Reel 14 (1of7))
  - Lactic Acid Bacteria B (Lab IV) (Box 16, Reel 15 (2of 7))
  - Lactic Acid Bacteria B (Lab IV) (Box 16, Folder 17 (4 of 7))
  - Lactic Acid Bacteria C. Experiments With Isolates (Lab IV) (Box 16, Reel 19(6 of 7))
  - Coliform Bacteria A-B (Lab VI) (Box 16, Reel 22 (1 of 6))
  - Coliform Bacteria B-F Experiments (Lab VI) (Box 16, Reel 23 (2 of 6))
  - Coliform Bacteria F Experiments (Lab VI) (Box 16, Reel 25 (4 of 6))
  - Coliform Bacteria F Experiments (Lab VI) (Box 16, Reel 26 (5 of 6))
  - Coliform Bacteria F Experiments (Lab VI) (Box 16, Reel 27 (6 of 6))
  - Acetic Acid Bacteria A-D Experiments With Isolates (Lab VII) (Box 16, Reel 28 (1 of 3))
  - Developmental History of Yeasts (Lecture X), 7/9/62 (Box 16, Reel 28 (5 of 5))
  - Acetic Acid Bacteria D. Experiments With Isolates (Lab VII) (Box 16, Reel 29 (2 of 3))
  - Patterns of Sugar Fermentations by Yeasts (Lecture XI), 7/11/62 (Box 16, Reel 30 (2 of 2))
  - Acetic Acid Bacteria D. Experiments With Isolates (Lab VII) (Box 16, Reel 30 (3 of 3))
  - Nitrogen-fixing Bacteria A-E (Lab VIII) (Box 16, Reel 31)
  - Classification and Nomenclature of Yeasts (Lecture XII), 7/13/62 (Box 16, Reel 31 (1 of 4))
  - Nitrogen-fixing Bacteria (Lab VIII) (Box 16, Reel 32 (2 of 2))
  - Corynebacteria, Nocardia, Mycobacteria, Arthobacteria (Lab IX) (Box 16, Reel 33)
  - Classification and Nomenclature of Yeasts (Lecture XII), 7/13/62 (Box 16, Reel 34 (4 of 4))
  - Luminous Bacteria (Lab XI) (Box 16, Reel 35)
  - Lactic Acid Bacteria A (Lecture XIII), 7/11/62 (Box 16, Reel 35 (1 of 3))
  - Lactic Acid Bacteria A (Lecture XIII), 7/11/62 (Box 16, Reel 36 (2 of 3))
  - Lactic Acid Bacteria A (Lecture XIII), 7/11/62 (Box 16, Reel 37 (2 of 3))
  - Lactic Acid Bacteria A, Section 2 Gram Stain (Lecture XIII), 7/11/62 (Box 16, Reel 37 (3 of 3))
  - Enterobacteriaceae or Coli Group A (Lecture XIV), 7/16/62;7/30/62 (Box 16, Reel 38 (1 of 3))
  - Enterobacteriaceae or Coli Group A (Lecture XIV), 7/16/62;7/30/62 (Box 16, Reel 39 (2 of 3))
  - Enterobacteriaceae or Coli Group A (Lecture XIV), 7/16/62;7/30/62 (Box 16, Reel 40 (3 of 3))
  - Role of Microorganisms in Nature, With Emphasis on Nitrogen Fixation (Lecture XV), 7/16/62 (Box 16, Reel 41 (1 of 1))
  - Fermentations of the Enterobacteriaceae (Lecture XXVII), 8/3/62;8/6/62 (Box 16, Reel 73 (4 of 4))
- Oversized Materials (Box 17)
  - Certificate for the American Society for Microbiology Honorary Member
  - Diploma for Honorary Degree of Doctor of Laws, University of California
  - Certificate for the National Medal of Science, 1963